Archiginnasio.0001 Archiginnasio.0001.ingest
Sezione dei manoscritti e dei rari
Specific information about the Bassi can be found in the collection of their deeds. The Bassi family originally came from Modena and moved to Bologna when Giuseppe Bassi, Laura's father, obtained citizenship after an extended stay there. Ultimately, Laura became the last representative of the family, since her only cousin Carlo Filippo Bassi—the son of her father's brother Giacomo—became a priest. To a large extent, the Bassis' deeds refer to Laura's inheritance, as Carlo Filippo's heir. The family of Domenico Veratti, or Verati, also originally came from Modena. They moved to Bologna in 1694 with Domenico Veratti's son Francesco, a general practitioner, and the father of Giuseppe, Laura's future husband. The various forms of the surname should be noted since, in the deeds, it is more frequently recorded as Verati; however, the spelling 'Veratti' prevailed over the course of time [9].
In the introduction to his memoirs, Ferdinando Veratti wrote that the family was called either Verati or Veratti [10] but the letters signed by Laura or other family members show that the first spelling was preferred. In this finding aid, we use 'Veratti' in references to Laura Bassi since that is now the customary spelling. The older spelling will be used in quotations taken from either primary or secondary sources.
The documents as they have come down to us from their direct descendants consist of the deeds and papers relating to various members of the Veratti family, who descended from the founder Domenico and his son Francesco, above all Paolo Veratti, Laura's son.
Originally, these documents were not organized either chronologically or by subject; rather, progressive numbering was handwritten on the documents sometime in the 20th century [11]. The material was little more than an unarranged stratification of various documents. They were initially organised by sorting them and then filing them under the names of the individuals they were ascribed to, following the chronology of the family and considering the descendants. In the case of Paolo Veratti—the best-known of Laura's children and the most frequently mentioned—the documents were also filed either according to subject or to significant events in his life. The two families' documents were interspersed with papers that cannot be associated either with the Veratti or the Bassi, or with any related subject, and these were therefore separated and added as miscellanea.
It should also be noted that the nucleus of the collection, bequeathed in the 1920s by the Mazzoni family, was later added to the material that was donated to the Archiginnasio in 1905 as part of the important gift of Arturo Gozzi [12]. It is not clear when this union of the two collections occurred, but we can guess that it was carried out fairly soon after the Mazzoni material was received, given that archivists of that period tended to arrange by subject rather than by provenance. Certainly it had occurred by 1962, when the first inventory of the Laura Bassi boxes was completed, inasmuch as the material was already included in that inventory.
Thanks to a list of materials included in the Gozzi donation, the identification of some of the documents that were added is possible. When the collection was arranged, that documentation was included, both because it was a consolidation and because the list is so cursory, it does not allow for the certain identification of all the material [13]. Whenever possible, the provenance is indicated in a note.
Elenco di consistenza
Delle singole serie che costituiscono il fondo si riportano l'indicazione degli estremi cronologici e la numerazione dei cartoni entro i quali le serie sono collocate.
1. Istrumenti relativi alla famiglia Bassi, 1591-1776, cartoni 1, 2
2. Istrumenti relativi alla famiglia Veratti, 1691-1830, cartoni 3, 4
3. Documenti relativi a Francesco Veratti, 1684-1708, cartone 5
4. Documenti relativi a Ferdinando Veratti, 1721-1788, cartone 5
5. Documenti relativi a Giuseppe Veratti, 1734-1742, cartone 5
6. Documenti relativi a Laura Bassi, 1732-1836, cartoni 6, 7
7. Documenti relativi a Giovanni Veratti, 1761-1800, cartone 8
8. Documenti relativi a Giacomo Veratti, 1772-1818, cartone 8
9. Documenti relativi a Paolo Veratti, 1765-1832, cartoni 9-11
10. Documenti relativi a Gaetano Veratti, 1806-1825, cartone 12
11. Documenti relativi a Francesco Veratti, 1830, cartone 12
12. Miscellanea, 1712-sec. XVIII, cartone 12
Extent description
Each series is described here by indicating the dates and the numbering of the boxes that contain the series.
1. Deeds referring to Bassi family, 1591-1776, boxes 1, 2
2. Deeds referring to Veratti family, 1691-1830, boxes 3, 4
3. Documents referring to Francesco Veratti, 1684-1708, box 5
4. Documents referring to Ferdinando Veratti, 1721-1788, box 5
5. Documents referring to Giuseppe Veratti, 1734-1742, box 5
6. Documents referring to Laura Bassi, 1732-1836, boxes 6, 7
7. Documents referring to Giovanni Veratti, 1761-1800, box 8
8. Documents referring to Giacomo Veratti, 1772-1818, box 8
9. Documents referring to Paolo Veratti, 1765-1832, boxes 9-11
10. Documents referring to Gaetano Veratti, 1806-1825, box 12
11. Documents referring to Francesco Veratti, 1830, box 12
12. Various materials, 1712-18th century, box 12
Note metodologiche
All'inizio dei lavori di riordino la documentazione era costituita da nove cartoni:
- due relativi a Laura Bassi, già ordinati ed inventariati
- tre relativi ai componenti della famiglia Veratti ed in particolare a Paolo Veratti, figlio di Laura
- quattro cartoni con istrumenti senza alcun ordine, relativi alle famiglie Bassi e Veratti.
Dai documenti relativi alla donazione [14] sembra che questa fosse la sistemazione con cui le carte pervennero all’Archiginnasio. In seguito ad una prima analisi risultò non esserci alcun nesso originale tra le carte per cui, trattandosi evidentemente di una raccolta e non di un vero e proprio archivio di persona, si è proceduto ad ordinare le carte secondo un ordine logico che permettesse un facile approccio alle stesse.
Innanzi tutto sono stati rispettati il riordino e l'inventariazione già dati ai cartoni relativi a Laura Bassi, in quanto funzionali è già utilizzati in passato dagli studiosi; sono state apportate solo alcune modifiche alla descrizione per renderla omogenea a quella restante del fondo. Sono stati riordinati i quattro cartoni di istrumenti, dividendo quelli relativi alla famiglia Bassi da quelli della famiglia Veratti, sistemandoli cronologicamente.
Sugli istrumenti sono state trovate delle segnature per libro e numero; non è stato trovato alcuno strumento di corredo relativo ma, ragionando per analogia, tale segnatura ha permesso di attribuire alcuni documenti a questa o quella famiglia e a verificare che si trattava comunque di una sistemazione grosso modo cronologica, che collocava prima gli istrumenti Bassi e di seguito gli istrumenti Veratti. Un’altra annotazione apposta su più atti notarili, "Gamberini notaio", non ha dato alcuna indicazione utile, se non per formulare l’ipotesi che tale notaio abbia potuto utilizzare i documenti da lui segnati per un fine non identificato.
Sono state infine riordinate le altre carte, rispettando la o le persone che le hanno poste in essere, tenendo in considerazione la cronologia delle stesse. Parte dei documenti erano praticamente non consultabili a causa del cattivo stato di conservazione e, prima del riordino, sono state oggetto di restauro nell'anno 2000. [15]
La documentazione è stata infine sistemata in 12 cartoni descritti ognuno analiticamente in base alle unità archivistiche che lo compongono (fascicoli, registri, singoli documenti) e sono stati messi in ordine cercando di rispettare la cronologia delle due famiglie:
cartoni 1-2: istrumenti relativi alla famiglia Bassi, i più antichi cronologicamente
cartoni 3-4: istrumenti relativi alla famiglia Veratti
cartone 5: carte relative alla famiglia Veratti (antecedenti all'inserimento nell'asse famigliare di Laura Bassi)
cartoni 6-7: carte relative a Laura Bassi
cartoni 8-12: carte relative ai figli e discendenti di Laura Bassi
Ad ogni nucleo è stata anteposta una breve introduzione esplicativa.
Per ogni singolo pezzo archivistico (fascicolo, registro, singolo documento) è stata data l'intitolazione, la data e la consistenza. L'intitolazione è stata riportata tra virgolette se desunta e trascritta dal pezzo medesimo; in assenza di una intitolazione originaria o comunque se presente ma non esaustiva ne è stata data una esprimente genericamente il contenuto, senza virgolette. La datazione di ogni pezzo è stata espressa, se possibile e indicativa, con anno mese e giorno. Nel caso di datazioni non originali o ipotizzate, queste sono state poste tra parentesi quadre. La consistenza è stata data nel caso di fascicoli tramite i documenti o le carte che lo compongono, mentre per i registri cartulando gli stessi. Anche nel caso di descrizione di documenti è stata data la relativa consistenza indicando le carte relative. Le eventuali note sono state apposte a piè di pagina.
Lo stato di conservazione di ogni pezzo è stato dato in nota nel caso in cui era necessario segnalarlo, in quanto l'archivio si trova attualmente in buone condizioni di conservazione, soprattutto dopo gli interventi di restauro.
Methodological notes
When the rearrangement began, there were nine boxes:
- Two referring to Laura Bassi, already arranged and described
- Three referring to the Veratti family members, especially to Paolo Veratti, Laura's son
- Four containing deeds, in no apparent order, pertaining to the Bassi and the Veratti.
According to the documents of the donation [14], the papers were apparently in this state when they arrived at the Archiginnasio. An initial study was carried out, and it found that there was no original order and that the material was a simple collection rather than a personal archive; therefore, the creation of an organizational system was undertaken so that a logical order would facilitate access to the documents.
The arrangement and description of the Laura Bassi boxes were retained, since they were already in place and had been used by scholars in the past; only a few changes were made to make the description similar to the one used for the other documents of the collection.
The four boxes containing the deeds were organized and the material divided between the Bassi and the Veratti, in chronological order. The deeds were found to be reference-signed by book and number; no finding aid was associated with them but, by analogy, it was possible to assign the documents to the appropriate family and make sure that they were chronologically arranged such that the Bassi deeds come first and the Veratti deeds later. One further handwritten note, "Gamberini notaio", can be found on several deeds, but it did not provide any useful information, other than that the lawyer was able to utilize the documents he signed for purposes that cannot be determined.
All the remaining documents were then arranged, assigning them to the person or persons who wrote them, in their chronological order. Some documents were difficult to read given their poor state of preservation and so, prior to undertaking this project, they were restored in 2000 [15].
The documents were placed in 12 boxes and then described (as either files, registers, or single documents) and ordered chronologically by family, as far as possible:
Boxes 1-2: deeds referring to the Bassi (the oldest ones ordered chronologically)
Boxes 3-4: deeds referring to the Veratti
Box 5: documents referring to the Veratti (before Laura married into the family)
Boxes 6-7: Laura Bassi’s documents
Boxes 8-12: documents referring to Laura Bassi’s children and descendants
Each group is introduced by a short explanatory note.
Each archival item (file, register, single document) was titled, dated and given a description of its physical extent. The title is in inverted commas if it was found in and transcribed from the same item; when there was no original title or if it can only be partially inferred, a title referring to the content was given, without commas. The date of each item, whenever possible and meaningful, is expressed as year, month and day. When dates are reconstructed or inferred, square brackets are used. The physical extent of files is given according to the documents or papers they are made of, while for registers the leaves were counted. Notes, if necessary, are after each item.
Thanks to its restoration, the collection is in good shape; when necessary, however, the particular state of an item's preservation is described in a note.
Note al testo
[1]
D'ora in poi indicata semplicemente come Laura Bassi.
[2]
Cfr. ARCHIVIO STORICO DEL COMUNE DI BOLOGNA (d'ora in poi ASCBo), Carteggio amministrativo, 1924, tit. XIV, rub. 5, sez. 3, prot. 12.688, "Biblioteca dell'Archiginnasio. Accettazione dai coniugi cav. Giulio Mazzoni ed Emma Veratti Mazzoni della donazione di lettere e scritti vari della celebre scienziata Laura Bassi Veratti e di altri personaggi della stessa famiglia Veratti".
[3]
La medaglia (cfr. cartone 6) fu disegnata da Domenico Maria Fratta e coniata dall'incisore Antonio Lazzari, come attestano le memorie e biografie.
[4]
Si tratta di circa 51 volumi presenti nella Biblioteca dell'Archiginnasio; cfr. elenco in: ASCBo, Carteggio amministrativo, cit., allegato C.
[5]
Cfr. RAFFAELLA TOMMASI, Documenti riguardanti Laura Bassi conservati presso l'Archiginnasio, "L'Archiginnasio", LVII, 1962, pp. 319-324.
[6]
Cfr. R. TOMMASI, Documenti riguardanti Laura Bassi, cit., p. 319. Esiste più di una biografia in merito a partire da "Notizie riguardanti la signora Laura Bassi Verati", copia di una lettera di Eustachio Manfredi, sec. XVIII/fine, cc. 2 (cfr. cartone 6) e dalle notizie presenti nel volume di memorie, compreso nel presente lavoro (cfr. cartone 5) e da cui sono state tratti gran parte dei dati, specialmente da Antonio Garelli per la sua biografia inserita in Lettere inedite alla celebre Laura Bassi scritte da illustri italiani e stranieri con biografia, Bologna, Tipografia G. Cenerelli, 1885, pp. 11-29. Si noti comunque come tutte le biografie a lei dedicate nei secc. XVIII e XIX sono incentrate sulla sua presentazione in pubblico, la laurea e la sua prima dissertazione, avvenimenti tutti avvenuti nell'arco del 1732, mentre poco o nulla viene detto sul resto della sua vita. Come sostiene Elio Melli, in Laura Bassi Verati: ridiscussioni e nuovi spunti, in Alma Mater Studiorum. La presenza femminile dal XVIII al XX secolo, Bologna, CLUEB, 1988, pp. 71-79, è l'epistolario di Laura Bassi la fonte primaria per avere un quadro più completo sulla sua vita.
[7]
Cfr. cartone 5, pezzo n. 3: "Memorie della famiglia Veratti di Bologna", 1726-1788 (rif. sec. XVII/metà - 1788), vol. manoscritto, pp. 102-105.
[8]
Cfr. cartoni 9-11.
[9]
A Bologna, ad esempio, esiste una via intestata appunto a Laura Bassi Veratti e la stessa Emma Mazzoni, che donò la raccolta, si firma nel 1924 "nata Veratti".
[10]
Ferdinando Veratti aggiunge "altrimenti detta de' Bonifazi" in quanto afferma che, per tradizione famigliare, si sosteneva che la famiglia traesse le sue origini da quella dei conti Sanbonifazi di Verona.
[11]
La numerazione è rimasta apposta sulle carte.
[12]
Cfr. BIBLIOTECA COMUNALE DELL'ARCHIGINNASIO, Archivio, Registri d'ingresso, Doni, 1905, nn. 261.717-261.877.
[13]
Si fa riferimento a volte sommariamente a "carte e fogli volanti in mazzo" o ad esempio a "poesie manoscritte ed altri scritti e memorie in onore della Laura Maria Caterina Bassi Veratti (un mazzo)", materiale identificabile solo in parte in quello conservato nel cartone 6, fascicolo 6.
[14]
ASCBo, Carteggio amministrativo, cit., allegati A-C.
[15]
Cfr. PIERANGELO BELLETTINI, Relazione del Direttore sull'attività svolta nel biennio 1999-2000, "L'Archiginnasio", XCIV-XCV, 1999-2000, pp. VII-XLVIII. a p. XXX-XXXI.
[16]
Nota redazionale: le abbreviazioni usate in riferimento alla documentazione indicizzata in questo inventario sono quelle tradizionalmente impiegate nella prassi archivistica.
Notes
[1]
From now on, Laura Bassi. (Author's note)
[2]
See ARCHIVIO STORICO DEL COMUNE DI BOLOGNA (henceforth ASCBo), Carteggio Amministrativo, 1924. tit. XIV. Rub. 5, sez. 3. prot. 12688, "Biblioteca dell’Archiginnasio. Accettazione dai coniugi cav. Giulio Mazzoni ed Emma Veratti Mazzoni della donazione di lettere e scritti vari della celebre scienziata Laura Bassi Veratti e di altri personaggi delle stessa famiglia Veratti."
[3]
The medal (inside box 6) was designed by Domenico Maria Fratta and cast by the engraver Antonio Lazzari, as documented in the biographies and memoirs listed in note 6 below.
[4]
There are 51 books, now at the Archiginnasio Library, as listed in ASCBo, "Carteggio amministrativo", op.cit., allegato C.
[5]
See RAFFAELLA TOMMASI, Documenti riguardanti Laura Bassi, "L'Archiginnasio,", LVII, 1962, p. 319-324.
[6]
See R. TOMMASI, Documenti riguardanti Laura Bassi, cit., p. 319. There are several biographies, "Notizie riguardanti la signora Laura Bassi Verati", a copy of a letter by Eustachio Manfredi written at the end of the 18th century, 2 leaves, (see box 6), as well as the memoirs included in our inventory (see box 5), which provided the greatest amount of information, particularly the biography by Antonio Garelli included in Lettere inedite alla celebre Laura Bassi scritte da illustri italiani e stranieri con biografia, Bologna, Tipografia G. Cenerelli, 1885, pp. 11-29. The fact should be stressed that all of Laura Bassi’s biographies of the 18th and 19th centuries focussed on her academic debut, her graduation and her first treatise. All these events took place in 1732; very little is told of the rest of her life. As Elio Melli wrote in his Laura Bassi Verati: ridiscussioni e nuovi spunti, in Alma Mater Studiorum. La presenza femminile dal XVIII al XX secolo, Bologna, CLUEB, 1988, pp. 71-79, Laura Bassi's letters are the primary source of information for a more thorough perspective on her life.
[7]
See box 5, item 3: "Memorie della famiglia Veratti di Bologna", 1726-1788 (referring to the mid-17th cent. – 1788), ms., pp. 102-105.
[8]
See boxes 9-11.
[9]
For instance, a road is named after Laura Bassi Veratti in Bologna, and even Emma Mazzoni, who bequeathed the collection, signed "née Veratti" in 1924.
[10]
Ferdinando Veratti adds "also called de' Bonifazi" when he writes that the family was traditionally believed to have descended from the Veronese count Sanbonifazi.
[11]
Page numbering is still visible.
[12]
See BIBLIOTECA COMUNALE DELL'ARCHIGINNASIO, Archivio, Registri d'ingresso. Doni, 1905, N. 261717-261877.
[13]
Sometimes the list simply refers to "documents and loose sheets of paper bundled together" or, for instance, to "one bundle of handwritten poems and other writings and memoirs for L.M.C. Bassi Veratti", which can hardly be described as the material contained in box 6, file 6.
[14]
See ASCBo, Carteggio amministrativo, cit., allegati A-C.
[15]
See PIERANGELO BELLETTINI, Relazione del Direttore sull’attività svolta nel biennio 1999-2000, "L'Archiginnasio", XCIV-XCV, 1999-2000, pp. VII-XLVIII. "Veratti Paolo" p. XXX-XXXI.
[16]
Editor's Note: Abbreviations used here are standard for archival practice.
Indice / Index
L'indice fornisce una lista di tutti i nomi di persona, ente e luogo presenti nell'inventario. / This index provides a list of all personal, corporate and place names found in the guide.
Accademici Agiati vedi Accademia degli Agiati (Roveredo)
Accademia degli Agiati (Roveredo)
Accademia degli Amanti della Botanica (Cortona)
Accademia degli Arcadi (Roma)
Accademia degli Ardenti (Bologna)
Accademia dei Dissonanti (Modena)
Accademia Emonia (Busseto)
Accademia degli Erranti (Fermo)
Accademia degli Erranti già Raffrontati
Accademia dei Fluttuanti (Finale di Modena)
Accademia Fulginia (Foligno)
Accademia degli Ipocondriaci (Reggio Emilia)
Accademia dei Placidi (Recanati)
Accademia dei Teopneusti (Correggio)
Accarisi, Floriano
Agli Puccetti, Laura
Albergati Fontani, Ginevra
Aldini, Giovanni
Aldrovandi, Filippo
Aldrovandi, Pier Iacopo
Aldrovandi, Pietro, vedi Aldrovandi, Pier Iacopo
Aldrovandi Marescotti, Carlo Filippo
Algardi, Francesco Antonio
Algardi, Giovanni
Amministrazione centrale del Reno
Ancona
Angela Matilde, suora, vedi Albergati Fontani, Ginevra
Angelelli, Teresa
Anosiro Minali
Antici, Tommaso, cardinale
Anton Maria da Pistoja, cappuccino
Ascoli
Aranti, Silvio
Archetti, Giovanni Andrea, cardinale
Assunteria di Abbondanza
Assunteria delle Acque
Assunteria di Governo
Assunteria di Sanità
Atti, Giuseppe
B.P.L.T.
B[...], Ferdinando
Baccelli, Liberato
Bacialli, Angelo Michele
Bajotti, Rinaldo
Baldi, Antonio
Bandiera, Giovanni Nicolò
Baroni, Innocenzo
Bassi, famiglia
Bassi, Carlo Filippo
Bassi, Felice
Bassi, Francesco
Bassi, Gaspare
Bassi, Giacinto
Bassi, Giacomo
Bassi, Giovanni
Bassi, Giuseppe
Bassi, Giuseppe Maria
Bassi, Laura
Bavari, Francesco Saverio
Bavoli, Giuseppe Maria
Bazzani, Matteo
Beccari, Giacomo Bartolomeo
Bellettini, Pierangelo
Bellini, Stefano
Belluzzi, Francesco Maria
Benati, Giorgio
Benelli, fratelli
Benelli, Francesco Maria
Benelli, Giuseppe
Benelli, Ludovico
Bergonzi Ranuzzi, Maria
Bernardi, Angelo Antonio
Bernardi, Antonio
Bertacini, Antonio
Bertinoro
Bertoloni, Antonio
Bertolotti, Angelo
Biasini, Giovanni
Bignami, Angelo
Blasi, Matteo
Bologna
Bonaccorsi, Giovanna
Bonazzi, Bartolomeo
Bonfioli Malvezzi, Alfonso
Bonini, Giovanni Battista
Borgognoni, Vincenzo
Borsari, Lorenzo
Branciforte Colonna, Antonio
Brighenti, Nicola Vittorio
Brizzi, Bernardino
Bruzzi, Elisabetta
Budrio
Busseto
Ca[...], Luigi
Cagnaroni, Giuseppe
Calvi, Jacopo Alessandro
Calvoli, famiglia
Calvoli, Giacomo
Calvoli, Giuseppe
Calvoli, Rosalia
Camerino
Canneto (Bari)
Canova, Giuseppe
Cantelli Cremonini, Giulia Teresa
Cantelli Tagliazucchi, Veronica
Canterzani, Sebastiano
Cappi, Maria Anna Margherita
Carini, Anna Caterina
Carlani, Carlo Antonio
Casignoli, Giovanni Domenico
Cassoni, Giuseppe
Castelli, monsignore
Castelli, Giovanni Battista
Castelli, Virginia
Castiglioni, Filippo
Castiglioni, Francesco Saverio, vedi Pio VIII, papa
Cavalleri, Domenico
Cavazza, Marta
Cavazzi, Bartolomeo
Cazzani, Pietro
Celsi, Giuseppe
Cenerelli, Giuseppe
Cesari, Rosa Maria
Cesena
Chierichetti Forti, Rosa
Chierichetti, Ermenegildo
Chierici, Francesco Maria
Cingoli
Collegio medico chirurgico di Bologna
Colli, Francesco
Colli, Giuseppe
Comelli, Giovanni Battista
Commissione cantonale di leva
Commissione dipartimentale di Sanità del Reno
Commissione provinciale di Sanità
Compagnia di Gesù (Modena)
Compagnia del Santissimo Sacramento (parrocchia di Santa Caterina)
Conventi, Benedetto
Corradini (Coradini) Zinanni, Maria Maddalena
Correggio
Corticelli, Alessandro
Cortona
Cospi, Girolamo
Costa, Paolo
Covi, Antonio
Cremonini, Francesco Antonio Bonaventura
Cremonini, Paolo
Cremonini, Teresa Maria
Cremonini Raggi, Angela
Crivelli, Giovanni
Cruciani, Ercole
Cruciani, Giulio
Cruciani, Nicola
Cuppini, Giuseppe
D.G.C.
D'Arèncourt, Garnier
Dalisa Caistria, pastore arcade
Dalla Volpe
Dalla Volpe
Dalle Donne, Maria
Davia, Giovanni Antonio, cardinale
Davia, Giuseppe
De Bandel, Giuseppe Antonio
De Bianchi, V.
De Buoi, Bartolomeo
De Bonifazi, famiglia
Devizi (De Vizi), Vittoria
Di Polignach, Melchiorre
Direzione delle Poste nel Dipartimento del Reno
Disvetro (Modena)
Dodi, Gaetano
Dodi, Pietro
Dugliolo
Emiliani, Luigi
Ercolani Ratta Garganelli, Elisabetta
F.P.
Fabri, Francesco
Fabri, Ranier Bernardino
Fano
Fanti, Mario
Fantoni, Pio
Fantuzzi, Giovanni
Farri, Francesco
Felici, Giovanni Battista
Fermo
Ferrara
Ferri, Antonio
Ferri, Giuseppe
Ferri, Gregorio Antonio
Fiandrini, Ottavio
Fieschi, Adriano
Finale Emilia
Fiorini, Anna
Fiorini, Domenico
Firenze
Fittili Lauri, Maria
Foligno
Formagliari, Alessandro